# **Rick Farrell**

## Sr. Systems Engineer

Lumberton, NJ - Email me on Indeed: indeed.com/r/Rick-Farrell/e172d14a01e0f4ea

I am an expert at all facets of Data-communications and Telecommunication. I have planned and implemented installations, testing, maintaining, troubleshooting and technology refresh based on requirements needed by customers. I offer you over 20 of experience in electronic repair/fault isolation, datacom/telecom (WAN/MAN), LAN/SAN networking and sales/marketing experience. With my many areas of expertise I would be a valuable asset to your company with unsurpassed loyalty and commitment to the short term and long term goals of your company.

#### WORK EXPERIENCE

### Sr. Systems Engineer

X-eeto Inc - October 2009 to August 2010

- Design physical layer infrastructure (electrical, communications and infrastructure)
- Manage ILOM
- Configure and test physical layer switching system
- Develop test plans
- Construct physical layout of the Patch and Test Facility
- Testing new circuit implementation
- · Cut-over new circuits into the Patch and Test Facility

## **IT Manager**

J and R Consulting Inc - September 2008 to March 2009

- Configure Windows2000 Servers and Microsoft Exchange Servers
- Managing and automating back-up and disaster recovery procedures
- Update all software to latest releases
- Implemented hardware refresh and lifecycle schedule
- Troubleshoot local and remote clients
- Installation of new workstations and deployment
- Manage network security and set policies
- Project management for integration of new hardware and software applications
- Manage VMware server configurations
- Managed OpenVPN clients
- SQL data synchronizing between corporate and remote clients
- Troubleshooting local and remote networks via VPN and remote desktop
- · Prepared formal technical drawings of complete system/equipment configurations and connectivity
- Analyzed data traffic to ensure full utilization of capabilities to isolate data congestion

#### **Technical Marketing Manager**

OnPATH Technologies - February 1998 to July 2008

- Responsible for assisting the sales force for requirements of customers
- · Installations of new systems
- Configuration of various routers (Cisco)
- Trouble shooting network faults to enable IP protocols for mandatory equipment functionality
- Performed upgrades on customer systems (hardware and software)

- Troubleshooting of complex multi protocol systems (WAN/MAN/LAN/SAN)
- Marketing research for new products and implementations
- Marketing Requirement Documents (MRD) for new product development
- · Automated scripting for Datacenters, Labs, Disaster Recovery environments to implement new systems
- Designed and implemented customer sites with Fibre Channel over Ethernet with remote trouble shooting abilities and monitoring of utilization to ensure full through-put and load balancing
- Consulting on best practices of Local Area Networks (LAN), Storage Area Network (SAN) and Wide Area Networks (WAN) and physical layer management
- Assisted Quality Assurance (QA) testing of newly developed hardware and software
- Sales Presentations with live demonstrations to customers and Partner sales seminars
- Produced all material and conducted customer training for 3, 5 and 10 day courses
- Professional services on various post sales implementations
- o Automated testing in a lab environment via scripting (EMC Product Verification LAB)
- o Automated rerouting via scripting for disaster recover with timed switching scripts (Lowe's Home Improvement Headquarters)
- o Migration of a datacenter to replace legacy switching systems to new replacement switching systems (Sabre/EDS)
- All trade show activities for AFCOM, Interop and AFCEA to include post trade show follow up Facilitated partnerships for joint ventures to increase sales
- · Managed and conducted Webcasting
- Conducted site surveys of datacenters to set forth recommendations and produce sales
- Performed integration of lightwave systems, testing and performance
- Installation and maintenance/installation of digital access cross connect systems
- Prepared formal technical drawings of complete system/equipment configurations and connectivity
- Analyzed data traffic to ensure full utilization of capabilities to isolate data congestion

#### Sr. Analyst Patch and Test Facility

ManTech - Miami, FL - September 1996 to February 1998

- Installation and relocation of the Path and Test Facility SOUTHCOM Headquarters from Panama to Miami
- Accountable for building of materials (B.O.M.) and tooling of the overall project
- Analyze the building of materials (B.O.M.) and initiated the procurement based on requirements and specifications outlined based on each application/circuit requirements
- Product procurement for critical equipment and infrastructure
- Provided updated circuit drawings for digital and analog circuits to encompass end user to end user circuit path
- Coordinated with remote sites for new circuit implementation and troubleshooting
- Installation of Analog and Digital (Sync and A-sync) circuits
- Installation and configuration of complex multiplexers and modems
- Circuit activations and provisioning of new requirements
- Testing of new circuits to remote destinations
- Digital Sync and A-sync troubleshooting of multi-protocol environments (RS-232, EIA530, EIA530A, RS-449, V.35, T-1, T-3, SONET, ATM)
- Open/tracked/assigned trouble tickets to the appropriate personnel for trouble shooting and fault isolation to limit downtime
- Provided situational reports to higher authority with accurate and updated information that leads to the corrective action procedure
- Coordinate trouble shooting of live circuits with local and remote personnel
- · Monitor circuit activity of local and remote capabilities to ensure efficient use of network resources
- Trainer for various test equipment to new personnel arriving to the Patch and Test facility

- System Administrator for the control system of the Patch and Test Facility
- Maintain circuit health, integrity and security of all communications to the SOUTHCOM Headquarters based on local and remote monitoring
- New circuit implementation and cutover post installation

## **Subsystems Repairer**

US Army, Strategic Electronic - September 1987 to August 1996

- Setup, maintain and de-installations of the system deployments to forward battlefield commanders
- Expert at reading schematics and block diagrams for equipment and system troubleshooting procedures
- Expert in troubleshooting electronic equipment to component level (de-multiplexers/multiplexers, modems, recorders, receivers, visicorders, modulators/de-modulators, computers/associated peripherals, physical layer switches, dynamic switches and a scoreboard)
- Calibration of data-recorders and receivers
- Resident expert on the MD-1130, TD-1306 and GSQ series workstations
- Expert in troubleshooting and isolating failures in data-com, telecom and IP networks
- Installation and maintenance of intelligence systems and networks in fixed facilities
- System administrator for various systems (ULLMAN/DCS, WINTERCAT)
- COMSEC custodian, responsible for all cryptology equipment facets (KIV, KG series equipment)
- Repair to LRU (Lowest Replaceable Unit) on all cryptology equipment
- · Satellite communications installation and maintenance
- Testing of new technological equipment to meet mission requirements in real time warfare

#### **EDUCATION**

## **AMP Physical Infrastructure Basics**

Learning Tree International

## ADDITIONAL INFORMATION

- Over 20 years experience in electronic repair and fault isolation
- Over 20 year of network installations, configuration and fault isolation
- Over 10 years Sales and Product Marketing experience
- Over 10 years as the official product trainer
- Experienced in Windows/Windows Server operating systems, HP-UNIX/SUN Solaris/Linux and MS-DOS
- Network routing experience with Cisco Catalyst series routers
- Well versed on oral and written communications with large and small groups of people
- Highly adaptable all facets of communications equipment
- Ability to complete tasks within deadlines and budget
- Excellent customer/employee relations skills; adept at interfacing with people of various cultures and social strata